<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Prototype | Alessandro Lacava]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.alessandrolacava.com/blog/categories/prototype/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.alessandrolacava.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-06-04T11:13:38+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.alessandrolacava.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alessandro Lacava]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Script.aculo.us Controls: Do Your Web Users a Favor]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.alessandrolacava.com/blog/script-aculo-us-controls-do-your-web-users-a-favor/"/>
    <updated>2011-10-26T17:32:32+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.alessandrolacava.com/blog/script-aculo-us-controls-do-your-web-users-a-favor</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Learn how to integrate Script.aculo.us web controls into your web applications to make the end-user experience more pleasant.</h3>

<p>In a previous DevX article, I wrote about the JavaScript framework Prototype, which aims to ease the development of dynamic web applications. That article ended with just a few words about Script.aculo.us, which is a fantastic UI library based on Prototype. This article gives Script.aculo.us its due by examining the web controls it provides: autocompleters, sliders, and in-place editors.</p>

<p>Script.aculo.us is a pretty big library, so no single article can cover it completely. However, the knowledge you will gain will enable you to leverage the power of Script.aculo.us web controls to improve the end-user experience.</p>

<p>Go to <a href="http://www.devx.com/webdev/Article/37574">DevX</a> to read the rest of the article: <strong>Script.aculo.us Controls: Do Your Web Users a Favor</strong>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Productivity Perks Behind Prototype's Popularity]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.alessandrolacava.com/blog/the-productivity-perks-behind-prototypes-popularity-2/"/>
    <updated>2011-10-26T17:29:31+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.alessandrolacava.com/blog/the-productivity-perks-behind-prototypes-popularity-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Learn how to leverage the popular Prototype JavaScript framework to speed up your AJAX-based development. You&rsquo;ll see how to use JavaScript in an object-oriented way.</h3>

<p>The Prototype home page claims that &ldquo;Prototype is a JavaScript framework that aims to ease the development of dynamic Web applications.&rdquo; By using many object-oriented paradigms such as class-driven development and inheritance to enable JavaScript application development, Prototype completely accomplishes its aim. In fact, this framework contains a lot of useful functionalities, which you cannot help but apply to every application you develop once you&rsquo;ve started using them.</p>

<p>Prototype&rsquo;s main claim to fame is its rich AJAX (Asynchronous JavaScript and XML) library, which simplifies the now popular Web development technique for making non-blocking calls to the server through JavaScript. (It topped the recent Ajaxian.com 2006 Survey as the most popular AJAX framework.) Of course, everything you can do with Prototype you also can do using plain JavaScript—upon which Prototype is built. But why would you want to complicate your life? For example, which would you rather type to accomplish the same task: document.getElementById(&ldquo;myElement&rdquo;) or $(&ldquo;myElement&rdquo;)? If you answered $(&ldquo;myElement&rdquo;), then read the remainder of this article for an in-depth discussion of some useful Prototype functions—$ is just one.</p>

<p>Go to <a href="http://www.devx.com/AJAXRoundup/Article/33174">DevX</a> to read the rest of the article: <strong>The Productivity Perks Behind Prototype&rsquo;s Popularity</strong>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sorting an Array of Objects With the sortBy Method of Prototype]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.alessandrolacava.com/blog/sorting-an-array-of-objects-with-the-sortby-method/"/>
    <updated>2006-11-20T16:34:48+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.alessandrolacava.com/blog/sorting-an-array-of-objects-with-the-sortby-method</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here is an example of how easy it is to sort an array of objects using the <code>Enumerable.sortBy</code> method of the Prototype framework:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript   ">var obj1 = {
  lastName : "Lacava",
  firstName : "Alessandro"
};

var obj2 = {
  lastName : "Brown",
  firstName : "John"
};

var obj3 = {
  lastName : "Simpson",
  firstName : "Bart"
};

var arr = [obj1, obj2, obj3];

//order by last name
var sorted = arr.sortBy(function(obj) {
    return obj.lastName.toLowerCase();
  }
);

var str = "";
sorted.each( function(obj, index) {
    str += index + 1 + " - " + obj.lastName + " " + obj.firstName;
  }
);

//display the elements ordered by last name
document.write(str);
</code></pre>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
