<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Aphorisms on Alessandro Lacava</title>
    <link>/categories/aphorisms/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Aphorisms on Alessandro Lacava</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 May 2008 13:49:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/categories/aphorisms/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Funny long jokes and aphorisms about programming (and programmers of course)</title>
      <link>/blog/funny-long-jokes-and-aphorisms-about-programming-and-programmers-of-course/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2008 13:49:38 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/funny-long-jokes-and-aphorisms-about-programming-and-programmers-of-course/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;here-are-some-funny-jokes-and-aphorisms-about-computer-programmers-and-programming-in-general&#34;&gt;Here are some funny jokes and aphorisms about computer programmers and programming in general:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A man is smoking a cigarette and blowing smoke rings into the air.  His girlfriend becomes irritated with the smoke and says, &amp;ldquo;Can&amp;rsquo;t you see the warning on the cigarette pack?  Smoking is hazardous to your health!&amp;ldquo;To which the man replies, &amp;ldquo;I am a programmer.  We don&amp;rsquo;t worry about warnings; we only worry about errors.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A programmer is walking along a beach and finds a lamp.  He rubs the lamp, and a genie appears.  &amp;ldquo;I am the most powerful genie in the world.  I can grant you any wish, but only one wish.&amp;ldquo;The programmer pulls out a map, points to it and says, &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;d want peace in the Middle East.&amp;ldquo;The genie responds, &amp;ldquo;Gee, I don&amp;rsquo;t know.  Those people have been fighting for millennia.  I can do just about anything, but this is likely beyond my limits.&amp;ldquo;The programmer then says, &amp;ldquo;Well, I am a programmer, and my programs have lots of users.  Please make all my users satisfied with my software and let them ask for sensible changes.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Funny short jokes and aphorisms about programming (and programmers of course)</title>
      <link>/blog/funny-short-jokes-and-aphorisms-about-programming-and-programmers-of-course/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2008 13:25:27 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/funny-short-jokes-and-aphorisms-about-programming-and-programmers-of-course/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;here-are-some-funny-jokes-and-aphorisms-about-computer-programming-and-programmers-in-general&#34;&gt;Here are some funny jokes and aphorisms about computer programming and programmers in general:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are only 10 types of people in the world: Those who understand binary, and those who don&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s always a long day, 86,400 won&amp;rsquo;t fit into a short.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Why do programmers always mix up Halloween and Christmas?&#xA;Because Oct 31 equals Dec 25.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Knock, knock.&amp;rdquo;&#xA;&amp;ldquo;Who&amp;rsquo;s there?&amp;rdquo;&#xA;very long pause&amp;hellip;&#xA;&amp;ldquo;Java.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Programming is like sex:&#xA;One mistake and you have to support it for the rest of your life.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why you shouldn&#39;t be concerned about optimization</title>
      <link>/blog/why-you-shouldnt-be-concerned-about-optimization/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Oct 2006 16:26:34 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/why-you-shouldnt-be-concerned-about-optimization/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When you were at the university or in any programming course, you&amp;ndash;like me&amp;ndash;were probably thought of the importance of&#xA;optimization. In the real world though, you should strive for writing good code&amp;ndash;possibly using bullet-proof&#xA;Design Patterns&amp;ndash;and defer optimization until later. Actually, you should optimize your code only if, after testing,&#xA;you realize that optimization is strongly necessary. There are three aphorisms concerning optimization that you cannot&#xA;but know:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;More computing sins are committed in the name of efficiency (without necessarily achieving it) than for any other&#xA;single reason, including blind stupidity.&lt;br /&gt;&#xA;&lt;strong&gt;William A. Wulf&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
